<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bosch-imap-savedate-00" ipr="trust200902">
<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>
<title abbrev="IMAP - SAVEDATE Extension">
Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) - SAVEDATE Extension
</title>

<author fullname="Stephan Bosch" initials="S." surname="Bosch">
	<organization>Dovecot Oy</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Lars Sonckin Kaari 10</street>
      <code>02600</code>
      <city>Espoo</city>
      <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>stephan.bosch@dovecot.fi</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date/>

<area>General</area>
<!--<workgroup>APPSAWG</workgroup>-->
<keyword>imap</keyword>
<keyword>savedate</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>This document adds a new capability called "SAVEDATE" to the Internet Message
Access Protocol (IMAP). It defines a new IMAP message attribute called 
'save date' that, unlike the existing 'internal date' attribute, always
indicates the moment at which the message was saved in its current mailbox.
The SAVEDATE capability extends the FETCH command with the means to retrieve the
save date attribute and it extends the SEARCH command to allow using that
attribute in searching criteria.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
<t>This document extends Internet Message Access Protocol
(IMAP) <xref target="IMAP4rev1"/> with a new capability called "SAVEDATE".
This capability adds a new IMAP message attribute called 'save date'. The save
date is the date and time at which a message was saved in the mailbox it
currently resides. The save date is similar to the existing internal date
attribute in that it is set at the time of delivery. However, the internal date
attribute can be set to an arbitrary value for messages delivered to the mailbox
using the APPEND command and it is usually copied from the source message for
messages delivered using the COPY command. In contrast, the save date attribute
is always set to the current date and time at the moment the message is saved in
the mailbox, irrespective of how the message is delivered and from where it
originates.
</t>
<t>The save date message attribute is useful for implementing automated removal
of messages from a mailbox after a configured amount of time. For that
application, it is necessary to know when the message was saved in the mailbox,
which cannot be reliably determined using the the internal date attribute.
</t>
<t>For example, a common client usage pattern is to move deleted messages to
a Trash mailbox [FIXME: reference to SPECIAL-USE RFC for discussion on
semantics of a "trash" mailbox (?)]; these messages are considered "deleted"
at the time they are moved to the Trash mailbox. In an effort to limit the size
of the Trash mailbox, a client may subsequently desire to permanently remove
(expunge) all messages in that Trash mailbox deleted before a certain time
(e.g. a configurable expiration interval). In that case, the internal date
attribute cannot be used, since it likely refers to the time at which the
message was originally received. The proper time comparison attribute should
instead be the time at which the message was saved to the Trash mailbox. Similar
usage patterns can be observed for Archiving solutions.
</t>
<t>The SAVEDATE capability extends the FETCH command and response to allow
retrieving the date and time at which a message was saved. Also, the SAVEDATE
capability extends the SEARCH command to allow searching messages with criteria
based on when it was saved in the mailbox.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
<t>In examples, "C:" indicates lines sent by a client that is connected
to a server.  "S:" indicates lines sent by the server to the client.
</t>
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="KEYWORDS"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="savedate" title="Save Date Message Attribute">
<t>The save date message attribute is the date and time at which the message was
saved in the mailbox it is now located in. Unlike the internal date
attribute defined by <xref target="IMAP4rev1"/>, this date and time value cannot
be set arbitrarily when a message is delivered by the IMAP APPEND command.
Also, when a message is delivered to the mailbox by the
<xref target="IMAP4rev1">IMAP COPY command</xref> or the
<xref target="IMAP-MOVE">IMAP MOVE command</xref>, the save date
attribute is not copied from the source message. Instead, the current date and
time at which the message is delivered to a mailbox MUST be used to set the
save date attribute. Once calculated, the save date attribute MUST NOT change
as long as the message is contained within the same mailbox.</t>

<t>This means that when the message is copied to another mailbox, the save date
of the message in source mailbox remains unaffected; only the new copy of the
message gets a new save date. Consequently, when the the message is moved to
another mailbox, either using the MOVE command or a command sequence involving
the COPY command <xref target="IMAP-MOVE"/>, the message always gets a new
save date in the destination mailbox.
</t>
<t>For some mailboxes, the underlying storage may not support the save
date message attribute. In such situations, the behavior is
implementation-defined. Using the internal date attribute instead is 
RECOMMENDED. [FIXME: This is what Dovecot currently does, but for a standard
this is inappropriate. It should probably indicate the lack of support with
a particular NO response code, or it could just return NULL or some other
special value].
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changes" title="IMAP Protocol Changes">

<section anchor="changes-capability" title="CAPABILITY Identification">
<t>IMAP servers that support this extension MUST include "SAVEDATE" in the
response list to the CAPABILITY command.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changes-fetch" title="FETCH Command and Response Extensions">
<t>This extension defines one new data item for the FETCH command:
<list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="SAVEDATE"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
  The save date of the message.
	</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>This extension defines one new data item for the FETCH response:
<list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="SAVEDATE"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
  A string representing the save date of the message.
  </t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Example:</t>
<?rfc needLines="4" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      C: A101 FETCH 998 (SAVEDATE)
      S: * 998 FETCH (SAVEDATE "01-Jan-2015 18:50:53 +0100")
      S: A101 OK Fetch completed.
]]></artwork></figure>
</section>

<section anchor="changes-search" title="SEARCH Command Extension">
<t> This extension defines three new search keys for the SEARCH command:
<list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="SAVEDBEFORE &lt;date&gt;"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
	Messages whose save date (disregarding time and timezone) is earlier than
	the specified date.
	</t>
  <t hangText="SAVEDON &lt;date&gt;"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
	Messages whose save date (disregarding time and timezone) is within the
	specified date.
	</t>
  <t hangText="SAVEDSINCE &lt;date&gt;"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
	Messages whose save date (disregarding time and timezone) is within or
	later than the specified date.
	</t>      
</list>
</t>
<t>Example:</t>
<?rfc needLines="7" ?>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      C: A102 SEARCH SAVEDON 28-Dec-2014
      S: * SEARCH 993 994
      S: A102 OK Search completed.
      C: A103 SEARCH SAVEDSINCE 28-Dec-2014
      S: * SEARCH 993 994 995 996 997 998 999 1000 1001
      S: A103 OK Search completed.
]]></artwork></figure>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="Syntax" title="Formal Syntax">
<t>The following syntax specification augments the grammar specified in
<xref target="IMAP4rev1"/>. It uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
notation as specified in <xref target="ABNF"/>. Elements not defined here are
taken from <xref target="IMAP4rev1"/>.</t>

<?rfc needLines="6" ?>
<figure><artwork type="ABNF"><![CDATA[
capability     =/ "SAVEDATE"

fetch-att      =/ "SAVEDATE"
msg-att-static =/ "SAVEDATE" SP date-time

search-key     =/ "SAVEDBEFORE" SP date /
                  "SAVEDON" SP date /
                  "SAVEDSINCE" SP date
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>There are no known additional security issues with this extension
beyond those described in the base protocol described in
<xref target="IMAP4rev1"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>The IANA is requested to add "SAVEDATE" to the "IMAP Capabilities"
registry located at
&lt;http://www.iana.org/assignments/imap-capabilities&gt;.</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Thanks to Bron Gondwana, Alexey Melnikov, Timo Sirainen, and Michael Slusarz
for reviews and suggestions.</t>
<t>More reviews are appreciated.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
<!-- References split into informative and normative -->

<references title="Normative References">
  <reference anchor='KEYWORDS'>
    <front>
    <title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
    <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
    <organization>Harvard University</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
        <street>Cambridge</street>
        <street>MA 02138</street>
      </postal>
      <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
      <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
    </address>
    </author>
    <date year='1997' month='March' />
    <area>General</area>
    <keyword>keyword</keyword>
		</front>

    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
    <format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
    <format type='HTML' octets='17491' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
    <format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
  </reference>

	<reference anchor='ABNF'>
		<front>
		<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
		<author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker'>
			<organization />
		</author>
		<author initials='P.' surname='Overell' fullname='P. Overell'>
			<organization />
		</author>
		<date year='2008' month='January' />
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name='STD' value='68' />
		<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5234' />
		<format type='TXT' octets='26359' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5234.txt' />
	</reference>

	<reference anchor='IMAP4rev1'>
		<front>
		<title>INTERNET MESSAGE ACCESS PROTOCOL - VERSION 4rev1</title>
		<author initials='M.' surname='Crispin' fullname='M. Crispin'>
		<organization /></author>
		<date year='2003' month='March' />
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3501' />
		<format type='TXT' octets='227640' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3501.txt' />
	</reference>

	<reference anchor='IMAP-MOVE'>
		<front>
		<title>Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) - MOVE Extension</title>
		<author initials='A.' surname='Gulbrandsen' fullname='A. Gulbrandsen'>
		<organization /></author>
		<author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='N. Freed'>
		<organization /></author>
		<date year='2013' month='January' />
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6851' />
		<format type='TXT' octets='15689' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6851.txt' />
	</reference>

</references>

<!--<references title="Informative References">
</references>-->
</back>

</rfc>
